Wyman, Donald, 1904-1993. Records of Horticulturist Donald Wyman, 1935-1970 (inclusive): A Finding Aid.
Records of Horticulturist Donald Wyman, 1935-1970 (inclusive).
Archives of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University, Jamaica Plain, MA 02130.
IV A-3 DW
Donald Wyman, 1904-1993.
10 Boxes
Donald Wyman served as the Arnold Arboretum horticulturist from 1935-1970. His papers reflect over 35 years of dedication to the study and advancement of horticulture within the academic community and in service of the gardening public at large. Wyman authored several books, including the acclaimed Shrubs and Vines for American Gardens, Trees for American Gardens, and the widely used and respected Wyman's Gardening Encyclopedia.
Access to Finding Aid record in Hollis Classic or Hollis.
Additional (firstname lastname) correspondence can be found by searching the Arnold Arboretum Correspondence Index.
Provenance: The majority of the material was acquired upon Dr. Wyman's retirement in 1970 with a small amount of biographical material added after his death in 1993. This collection was transferred from the Arnold Arboretum’s departmental holdings to the Arboretum’s Archives in 1984.
Terms of Access
Researchers seeking to examine archival materials are strongly encouraged to make an appointment. The Director, or an office of origin, may place restrictions on the use of some or all of its records. The extent and length of the restriction will be determined by the Director, office of origin, and the Archivist and will be enforced equally for all researchers.
Donald Wyman (1904-1993) served as Horticulturist of the Arnold Arboretum from 1935-1970. Taking responsibility at a difficult period, following the deaths of founding director Charles Sprague Sargent in 1927 and Keeper of the Arboretum E. H. Wilson in 1930, in the midst of the Great Depression Wyman lead a comprehensive plant labeling and mapping program and initiated a thinning of old and declining specimens. As head of living collections, Dr. Wyman promoted and introduced many species and varieties of plants new to the Arboretum and in some cases to the United States.
Wyman received a B.A. in horticulture from Pennsylvania State College, and at Cornell University received an M.A. in forestry, and a Ph.D. in horticulture in 1935. His work at the Arnold Arboretum focused on the scientific evaluation of ornamental trees and shrubs, and the practical application for public consumption through lectures, publications, publicity, and various means including field classes at the Arboretum for 35 years. A prolific writer, Wyman published hundreds of articles and as editor of the Bulletin of Popular Information and Arnoldia, which achieved broader circulation for the Arboretum publication. Wyman wrote several books, including the acclaimed Shrubs and Vines for American Gardens, Trees for American Gardens, and the widely used and respected Wyman's Gardening Encyclopedia.
Donald Wyman was president, director, and trustee of the American Horticultural Society and trustee of the Massachusetts Horticultural Society. His contributions to horticulture were recognized with the top medals of the American Horticultural Society—the Liberty Hyde Bailey Medal, the Massachusetts Horticultural Society--the George Robert White Medal, and the Royal Horticultural Society of London--the Veitch memorial Gold Medal.
Dr. Wyman was concerned with maintaining and developing the living collections, editing the Arboretum's Bulletin of Popular Information and Arnoldia, and promoting the Arboretum through publicity, publications, and lectures. Wyman focused on advancing the science of horticulture and the practice of gardens and arboreta through published books and articles. Wyman's papers reflect these activities. The research files he created are arranged in alphabetical sequence. Topics include detailed lists of hurricane damage to Arboretum plants for the years 1954, 1960, and to Mt. Auburn Cemetery for 1938; plant propagations of William H. Judd, 1945-1947; guides, brochures, postcards, and lists of special plant collections of arboreta and botanical gardens of the world; Arboreum plant collection notes 1948-1969; current Arboretum planting lists, 1968-1970; and lilac fertilizer experiments, 1938.
The collection is maintained in the alphabetical sequence created by Dr. Donald Wyman.
- (Box 1)
- Botanical Gardens and Arboreta, Folder 1 -
- U. S. National Arboretum / Botanical Gardens Questionnaire, Folder 2 -
- Arboreta - Golden Gate Park / Highland Park, Folder 3 -
- Arnold Arboretum Collections - Notes, Folder 4 -
- Arboretums and Botanical Gardens 1957, Folder 5 -
- Seeds collected by Jose Diem in Argentina 1952 (Summary), Folder 6 -
- Books, Folder 7 -
- (Box 2)
- Biographical Sketches, Folder 1 -
- Autumn Color Notes, Folder 2 -
- Bulbs, Folder 3 -
- Columnar Trees, Folder 4 -
- Sources for Columnar Trees, Folder 5 -
- Conifers - Dwarf, etc. Including Bonsai, Folder 6 -
- Contacts, Folder 7 -
- Current Planting Lists, Folder 8 -
- Dutch Elm Disease, Folder 9 -
- Espalier, Folder 10 -
- Export Regulations, Folder 11 -
- Fences, Folder 12 -
- (Box 3)
- Fertilizers, Folder 1 -
- Flower Shows, Folder 2 -
- Massachusetts Horticulture Flower Show 1977, Folder 3 -
- Flower Show - Christmas 1956, Folder 4 -
- Flower Show 1958 - 1959, Folder 5 -
- Christmas 1960, Folder 6 -
- Bound personal notes on plant genera, Folder 7 -
- (Box 4)
- Fragrant Plants, Folder 1 -
- Fruits and Nuts, Folder 2 -
- Ground Covers, Folder 3 -
- Hardiness, Folder 4 -
- Hedges, Folder 5 -
- Hurricane Damage to the Arnold Arboretum, Folder 6 -
- Hurricane, Folder 7 -
- Instructions to Secretary, Folder 8 -
- Kalmia, Folder 9 -
- (Box 5)
- Landscape Judges Course 1960, 1963 Pittsburgh, PA and Boston, MA, Folder 1 -
- Miscellaneous, Folder 2 -
- (Box 6)
- Plant Introduction and Introducers, Folder 1 -
- Plants that have died in the nursery, Folder 2 -
- Mulches, Peat Moss, Etc., Folder 3 -
- List of important Nursery Catalogues 1964, Folder 4 -
- Arnold Arboretum Plant Introductions 1923 -1972, Folder 5 -
- 1953 list of plants requested from nurseries, Folder 6 -
- (Box 7)
- Plant Propagation - Notes, Folder 1 -
- Plant Names, Folder 2 -
- Plants given to Harvard University, Folder 3 -
- Plant and Seed Distribution, Folder 4 -
- Plants to be given away, Folder 5 -
- Plant Quarantine - Interstate, Folder 6 -
- Plants from European Nurseries prior to 1960 - 1966, Folder 7 -
- Plant Quarantine - Importations from Foreign Countries, Folder 8 -
- Information about New Plants requested in the Arnold Arboretum, Folder 9 -
- (Box 8)
- Plants requested for the Arnold Arboretum, Folder 1 -
- Propagation 1945 -1947 (plants propagated by William H. Judd.), Folder 2 -
- Sources for Plants Requested, Folder 3 -
- Positions opened or wanted, Folder 4 -
- Sources for rare plants, Folder 5 -
- Rootstocks, Folder 6 -
- Soil Sterilization and Testing, Folder 7 -
- Tsuga, Folder 8 -
- (Box 9)
- Photographs of Donald Wyman, Folder 1 -
- Arnoldia 53 (3) 1993 p. 2. Remembering Donald Wyman, Folder 2 -
- Letter to Gary Koller from D.W. (May 1990), Folder 3 -
- The Arboretums and Botanical Gardens of North America, Folder 4 -
- Memorandum 1969, Folder 5 -
  "Making a planting List" memorandum from Dr.Wyman October 28, 1969. "Searching for New Plants" memorandum from Dr. Wyman October 30, 1969.
- Ulmus, Folder 6 -
- Vaccinium, Folder 7 -
- Viburnum, Folder 8 -
- Weeds and Weed Eradication, Folder 9 -
- Weigela, Folder 10 -
- (Box 10)
- Notebook containing Crab Apple Notes
  sent to Donald Wyman by Arie F. den Boer from Des Moines, Iowa. Received June 16, 1961.